called order the regular scheduled meeting of the Minor City Council from Monday, May 2, 2022.
Public input and scheduled personal appearances, none.
Three, consent agenda staff recommends we improve on its four and five.
Second.
Aye.
No quote.
Sender.
Aye.
Six.
Budget amendment.
22-24 general fund grants, police department, carry over.
All right, we got two different parts of this.
The first part is the police department.
They received $17,000 for a total police car.
But they want to amend to be able to replace that car.
And then they also got reimbursement.
Of course.
I'm sorry.
I lost more words here.
What's that?
Probably $20 is a real punishment.
The school resource officer's training.
The second half of that is we had a budget amendment 22-07 at the beginning of the year,
where we realized the grant fund carry over was greater than what we had anticipated.
It would be.
We amended it to allow them to expand that.
That.
And
This.
That.
But is.
It.
The.
r.
Thank you.
So, go.
Hi.
Thunder.
Davis.
Estep.
Parker.
Hi.
Seven.
Presentation by Mon.
Economic Services Mades.
From Mr. Heather Lowe.
We being Mayor Parker.
From Council members.
Thank you for allowing me to be here and talk to you.
My name is Heather Lowe and I am here as a representative of the Executive Committee
of the Miami Area and all of the development services.
I'm also joined by Dr. Kyle Stafford.
We're member.
And the reasons.
Thank you.
also on a board. So our chairman chief, Ed Will Cook, since her apologies, she cannot be here tonight,
but wanted me to extend that apology. So before that, again, I would just like to personally thank
each of you for your time and dedication. I know firsthand what is involved in that. I am Mary
to pass council members, so I'm going to hold that against me. But I would like to say this how
excited I am about the movement. I would consider it a little bit of a movement happening in
my memory now, and the momentum that's happening. So great things are going on in my
hand and I truly believe that it's just getting started. So the purpose of us being here tonight
is to just provide some communication to you, share our area of focus for 2022 and 2023 for our
organization, and then update you on our search efforts for our new director. And once again, just to
let you all know how excited our board is to continue partnering with the city on this moment
of progress that's happening. So I would first like to give just a little bit of a story lesson of
mates. Just to remind her that mates was created back in 1985 with the closing of the F. Goodrich.
It was Mayor Dr. Bill Goodman at that time. And he got together some gentleman at Chuck Goldenberg.
My father-in-law was in that group several community leaders and just tasked them with the
job of how to we keep my other from just drying up. So I'm being honest to me, I didn't know until I was
visiting with my father-in-law that these gentlemen would be daily for months. They met daily. They went through
a large fantasy study, trying to learn what business we look like, what does the structure of this
organization look like, how do we work in partnership with the city to make this happen. So with that,
mates was born. We are a 5-0-1-C-3 organization. And for over 35 years now, mates has provided advice,
loan funding to major local business in addition to assisting the city with recruitment of industry.
I think one of their most prized projects was the recruitment of Bayliner at the time,
which is now Chuck and Lorraine. So this is a little history lesson on mates. I also wanted to share
with you our board structure and just to make sure everybody's aware of who is on the mates board and
how it's structured. So we do have an executive committee and then board members. And so it's really
important to us as a board to have a nice variety of representation in the community. So as you can see,
we have a nice sampling of tribal partners, my moped.
of schools in the O and two city representatives on our board and then also several community
business overs. So at the end of 2021, very beginning of 2022, we realized we needed to put
more effort into defining our focus. So we engaged with the consultant and economic development
director Jim Fram. He has over 35 years in the economic development industry. So we engaged
with him, he led us through a strategic mining exercise. And then we continued the conversation
about a month later and we invited city representatives, community stakeholders. We did not
want it to just be our board coming up with that focus. We wanted input from the city
we wanted input from community stakeholders. What is the purpose of mates? What is our focus
need to be? We realized we were trying to maybe accomplish this much in the last several years.
Maybe we need to have more of a focus more of a scope. So with that we created these six
initiatives that I would like to just briefly touch on tonight. And the first one being business
retention and expansion. So there's a statistic that shows nationally that 75% of all new jobs in a community
come from existing businesses are located here. So we actually, some pretty exciting things are
happening on this front just within the last three or four weeks of month and for this month,
mates in the city has been collaborating very closely, working with two different local companies
and expansion networks. So that's really exciting and just a perfect example of how that's going on now.
This really is one of our top priorities and our focus, our new director,
to really be taking care of the industry that's here. When you're taking care of the employers that are
here and helping them solve their problems, that's when the recruitment of new business kind of also
takes care of itself because that's the first thing they're probably, they're asking that's existing
business here and they want to see that they're going to be well taking care of. Workforce will be a huge
priority that we want our new director to focus on as we all know it's a major issue for all employers right now.
So we really want our new director jumping in, meeting with our employers and working along with the city
and working along with our wonderful resources we have here locally. One of the first meetings we want to
ask this person with this, let's get all of these parties in the same room. Let's get any of you,
let's get our high schools, let's get the Northeast Tech, let's get the major factors and figure out
how we can capitalize on all of those resources.
and help solve this workforce issue and provide them the trained workers that they need
and that they're lacking. So workforce will be another main focus and of course as always
recruitment of new businesses will continuing working closely with the city and Tyler
answering RFPs trying to attract that new business coming in also. Collaboration with our partners
is also going to be a major focus. Collaborating with U.S. the city,
collaborating with our tribal partners, county relationships. That's going to be a huge focus for us
and our new director. Increased revenue like all organizations we have to keep our revenue up.
We want to work hard to continue to increase that revenue so we can maintain the effectiveness
of our organization and then just our marketing and value proposition just continuing to tell our story.
We recognize that we can do that and prove it and increase that and so that's going to be our focus.
Something that you can expect from our new director will definitely be quarterly updates to you
and along with these strategic initiatives where implementing metrics so that we can actually
measure the success and measure the progress so you can expect a quarterly update from our new
director with those metrics and letting you know what's going on and a little more measured approach to
our effectiveness. So lastly, I have just a very brief update as you know we are in between your
directors. We are in the final stages of our search process for our U.C.O. and President. We also
engage with Jim Graham for this search. She has an extensive network in this industry and the process
began about 45 days ago, advertised the position nationally regionally and then even locally. So we
cast a very wide net, we have narrowed it down and we are as you know this process is culminating this
week and we definitely look forward to your participation in that process. So in closing I would
just like to thank you all, thank the city for being a long time supporter of Maine and we look forward to
continue successful relationship. Do you have any questions on myself or not just that?
Well as you know I've been the mayor about two years, a little over, no almost two years and coming in
not a big fan of Maine's made that pretty clear right off the bat.
but I've seen the work, it's being put in, I've seen the process, it's been put in to hire this next CEO and President.
It's going to be a huge hire, it's going to be big I think for the people sitting up here on who that person is and how we move forward.
So I am excited to see who that person is and see where we go because as you said, we are on a great trajectory right now as a community.
I see great things happening in our future and I'm all big excited to see what this person can do and we're big, we're big puzzle and this is another piece that needs to be put in there.
I guess we're going to need to be so I'm excited.
I can't wait to meet them on Wednesday.
They're right, Wednesday three to five we're on the bottom.
So I hope everybody can make it to the visit with them.
You're down to clues that right.
So you're saying by this, try to know who that person is.
We will have a very close.
That is our goal.
Yes.
But I'm excited because I really think that I think a change was needed.
And I'm glad it's finally taken place and I look forward to the new person and where we go.
So I'm excited about it.
I think the only comment I'd like to make in wrapping up is these two individuals that are with us tonight for
made our extremely instrumental in moving mental organization forward.
Heather Lillard is a force to be reckoned with and is you talk about a force multiplier.
She can get things done.
And of course, Dr. Stavard has brought tremendous institutional knowledge and his experience in this arena has been fantastic for this community.
You're just really shining light and helping us figure out what do we want to be?
We grow up.
So big kudos to these two and thank you all for being here tonight.
Thank you so much for all your commitment to this community and to me.
I would like to say too that I would ask that the council, whoever they hire,
let's give this personal chance.
Let's give this personal opportunity.
If we don't like what we're seeing, we can voice that.
We've let it out.
But I know they put a lot of time in front of this and I really like first of give this personal chance to see if we can get this rolling.
See if we can get this this organization rolling like it should have been many years ago.
I think with the group that's there, of course she put up the group that's executive committee of the board.
And I know there's some people on there that believe like we believe and trying to get this going like we want.
So any other questions for us?
Thank you guys.
Heather.
Thanks.
Thank you.
I don't think there's going to be any problem with this group voice in Caliphill.
It may not be always pleasant, but we voice it because we care.
That's the way people work through it.
It may not always agree on it, but we can agree to disagree and for the betterment of our community.
That's a goal.
Thank you.
Thank you all very much.
Great.
Crawford Associates Engagement Liter, for Accounting Services in 2223.
So it's same as the same one.
Just two proof.
Please.
He stepped.
All right.
Sunder.
Noble.
Hi.
Davis.
All right.
We're agreement with my of a tribe of Oklahoma for utility repayment.
Would you do a proof?
Second.
He stepped.
Hi.
The whole.
Sunder.
All right.
Ten.
In user license agreement and limited warranty with in visionware and corporate management software
from month of library, authorize the manager.
Yes.
It's really simple though.
We're just upgrading our prep management system to something a little more current.
Our current, then we have right now just outdated.
So this is just to change over to a different company.
And it also gives us a few more things that we don't have like mobile printing.
Some people can print for on any mark to the library come in and pay for it.
It will print out for them.
So that's kind of nice.
It don't have to worry about saving it to a last child.
Everything.
It works with all of our existing hardware.
So there's no extra expense there on anything like that.
We don't have to change anything out.
I'm assuming there's a cost associated.
Is it already budgeted?
Yes.
Motion to approve.
Thank you.
All right.
I'll have an ordinance 2222-07 establishing authority and procedure for the closing of the public way.
Alley street reasement.
Reserving the right to be reopened the same.
Providing for fees.
Repeating ordinance in whole or apart.
In conflict.
Herewith.
And declaring emergency.
So this is really in conjunction with what we're going into executive session for.
But in looking at numerous issues relating to that one of the things we found is that the city does not have a mechanism for closing a street or alley or easements or whatever.
And so this gives us that mechanism to do it.
require, if we're wanting to close an actual street, for instance, then we have to have
another ordinance that deals specifically with that.
This just gives us the general parameters of how we're going to do that.
And basically it just mirrors what the state law provides.
We have a copy of that.
Yes.
What's the action here?
We have to be to approve this ordinance, and then the next agenda item would be to approve
it as an emergency.
Second.
Number.
Five.
Eight.
Twelve.
Emergency cause of 2020-07.
Establishing authority and procedure for the closing of the public way.
All these street or easement.
Reserving the right to reopen the same.
We're riding for fees, we're building ordinances and whole.
We're in part and conflict where we're here with and declaring emergency.
So this is just the emergency clause to the ordinance.
We just put it into effect.
Right now.
Any questions?
Second.
Number.
Double.
Davis.
E step.
Parker.
13.
Mary's nomination to appoint Rick Aldrich to the man of housing authority.
Turned to expire 13.
225.
Mike emotions.
Second.
clinical.
He.
He's step back.
Davis.
I.
14.
In the other new business that may.
A sudden supposed to be this agenda.
15.
Staffed.
16.
Mayor.
Council committee.
Enhotsments.
Okay.
Say something.
Yep.
So.
I got a phone call the other day from.
the retired fireman.
That's helping work on.
Saving the.
Bow helped me out tremendously on this, but I think the fundraising money that they raised in the hoops
They got a jump through to access it to buy something and for that
Having a weight to get it up
on an agenda to be approved, I think something needs to be changed
different because it's not city money, it was a fundraiser, so they should
be able to spend it how they think fit, the guys that are working on it. I don't
know why the council has to prove the way they spend it. You know, there was a truck
they wanted to buy to do the conversion. The seller wasn't going to hold it
to tell the council approved it, so Bo was able to help out and get that done to
find local carlots to buy it, get it, and then take the proper steps to pay for it.
But if these gentlemen are going to work on this thing on shift, when they're at the
fire station, if they need to run to a rallies, or if there's something that they need
to buy for it, I don't feel we should have to approve their purchases. It's
fundraising money. It's not coming out of a budget anymore. You know, it's all money
that was donated by private citizens. So I don't know what we have to do. I was told
legally there or something had to be done. There's a few names that were thrown around
there, Bo knows more of it, but something needs to happen to where these guys can.
They have access to the files.
I was approached by the same retired farm in this weekend. We've already approved them to
do the work, so it's what else do we have to do to actually get them the funding audit?
Well, I think that's as a council we should know by how much was raised, how much was raised,
and t-shirt sales, how much was raised in the selling of the food, the auction, how much they have to work
with. I mean, if they're within their limits of the money that have to work with, they should be able
to spend it how they see fit.
I guess, biolink concern with it would be to make sure that it's tracked.
I'm not for us, but I think they should be able to call their cheap and say, hey, we're going to go,
we need this. I think they should be able to go their cheap and their cheap can go to whoever they need to
spend the money that was raised.
Well, I don't have a problem. I just think it has to be given to someone, but whether it be the
secretary at the bottom of the apartment, or whoever the wrong would choose, I don't care, but somebody
could just track where every penny goes, because if 10 cents is spent the wrong way, it's
going to sit and find it out, 30% of the dollar's going to pay.
Well, I'm not saying that he might spend it wrong, but I'm just saying those questions
about it. So, and I don't know if I don't know if the city was asked, the money was asked me
putting the city, if I don't know how it got to work and got it.
But I think there are options that when this was set up, it could have been done in the city
account or not a city account. I think there was determination.
made by the committee that's redoing the truck to put it in a city account. I
can certainly get with Jill and Mike and we can talk about if there's an alternative at
this point if we want to pull the money out of the city account and put it somewhere else
we're happy to do that but if it's going to go into a city account then we're going to follow
all the state and municipal laws. But other than that I bet we've got some options and we'll
look into it and then there's some options and Jill can probably help me tell you one options
there are happy to do it. I don't want to have to jump through hoops but I do want to be tracked
that way if somebody comes back then you can say here where was that? Sure. The other piece of
that is can we have something like that for our next council meeting so it doesn't have to be
drug out for a long time? I think we should figure it up before that. Okay. How about we come and
give it up. Data what we did in the next council meeting and that's fine. How much money has been
raised so far? June 580. That's not counting shirts and that's we still that's included in the auction
and the food that is sold. Correct. Then we've got an insurance company that's going to give us a grant
for a few thousand we have to receive that gift. We've spent 6,500. We've got a discount on the truck,
right? I mean if we hurryed up and bought it Friday we got a heck of a discount on it. Yeah.
I think Harpado. Harpado. Harpado group helped out. I'm asking if that's a partial hard
stepped up and was able to do that because this is a city account at any time the city is purchasing a vehicle
we have to do a W9 is a non-tax building fee and he knows how to do that because that's what he does.
So he was able to take care of that purchase it and we'll be working with Harp to purchase to be from Harp this week.
The individual was an interest in that. Right. Yeah. He wasn't interested in waiting. I appreciate you helping out.
Well, I'm going to give you a cool call. I'm going to help out a bunch to set some of the firefighters mind that he's
we just got to figure out whether or not jump in through to me who's to access money that was raised for a project.
I'm excited about this project. I can't wait to say it down in the run and
and absolutely our guys actually put their blood sweat and tears into it. I think they're all excited for that.
You're going to have it down by the Christmas break? Yes.
It's probably yes, we're all right.
Hey, Dwight says we need to pull that boat out and put it inside.
The boat can get wet.
truck in there's that way they weren't on it, I have lights they weren't all night
it's cool that you guys found it, you can get it, so if any other American council statements are
or now it's built, no, I'm good today, I told you I was going to do it
so Dean said he made it to communications, you didn't steal my thunder tonight, I'll let you out
huge thank you to everyone involved in mural fest, 66, tremendous outcome, the murals
look fantastic, artists were amazing live music, food trucks, lots of kid activities, they had a train running up and down
the street, had a car show, great turnout, it was really cool, everybody thank you thank you to all involved
I'm sitting here looking at Courtney but thank you to parks, thank you to utilities, thank you to PD, my gosh the list goes on and on
everybody that comes together when we do these events and pull that off, but it was fantastic, so good job everybody
that is it, 18 million I'll be continuing from council chambers, recommendations in the staff room, purpose of the next second